Reading Journey Down the Mekong
Part 1 The Dream and the Plan My name is Wang Kun.
Ever since middle school,
my sister Wang Wei and I have dreamed about taking a great bike trip.
Two years ago she bought an expensive mountain bike and then she persuaded me to buy one.
Wang Wei soon got them interested in cycling too.
After graduating from college, we finally got the chance to take a bike trip.
I asked my sister, "Where are we going?"
It was my sister who first had the idea to cycle along the entire Mekong River from where
it begins to where it ends.
I am fond of my sister but she has one serious shortcoming.
She can be really stubborn.
Although she didn’t know the best way of getting to places,
she insisted that she organize the trip properly.
Now I know that the proper way is always her way.
I kept asking her, "When are we leaving and when are we coming back?"
I asked her whether she had looked at a map yet.
Of course she hadn’t; my sister doesn’t care about details.
So I told her that the source of the Mekong is in Qinghai Province.
She gave me a determined look - the kind that said she would not change her mind.
When I told her the air would be hard to breathe and it would be very cold,
she said it would be an interesting experience.
I know my sister well.
Once she has made up her mind, nothing can change it.
Finally, I had to give in.
Several months before our trip,
Wang Wei and I went to the library.
We found a large atlas with good maps that showed details of world geography.
From the atlas we could see that the Mekong River begins in a glacier on a Tibetan mountain.
At first the river is small and the water is clear and cold.
Then it begins to move quickly.
After it leaves China and high altitude,
the Mekong becomes wide, brown and warm.
As it enters Southeast Asia, its pace slows.
It makes wide bends or meanders through low valleys to the plains where
rice grows.